<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon vpon the words of Saint Paul, Let euerie soule be subiect vnto the higher powers wherein the Popes soueraigntie ouer princes, amongst other errors, is briefly but sufficiently refuted, and the supremacie of the King, by cleare euidence and strong proofe auerred, to the silencing of the aduersarie, and satisfaction of the indifferent Christian, not blinded with partialitie and preiudicate opinion / by Thomas Ingmethorpe.</title>
            <author>Ingmethorpe, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14088.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121083</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22922737</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22922737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04031)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25909)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 840:4 or 1777:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon vpon the words of Saint Paul, Let euerie soule be subiect vnto the higher powers wherein the Popes soueraigntie ouer princes, amongst other errors, is briefly but sufficiently refuted, and the supremacie of the King, by cleare euidence and strong proofe auerred, to the silencing of the aduersarie, and satisfaction of the indifferent Christian, not blinded with partialitie and preiudicate opinion / by Thomas Ingmethorpe.</title>
                  <author>Ingmethorpe, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Field for Robert Mylbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A4(-A1) B-E4.</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 840:4 identified as STC 14088a.</note>
                  <note>Item at 1777:30 imperfect: lacks signature A4.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in: the Folger Shakespeare Library and New College (University of Edinburgh). Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England) --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25909:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25909:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON VPON THE WORDS OF SAINT PAVL:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let euerie ſoule be ſubiect vnto the higher powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Popes ſoueraigntie ouer Princes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other errors, is briefly but ſufficiently refuted; and the Supremacie of the King, by cleare euidence and ſtrong proofe auerred; to the ſilencing of the aduerſarie, and ſatisfaction of the indifferent Chriſtian, not blinded with partialitie and preiudicate opinion:</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS INGMETHORPE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Pet. 2.13.</bibl>
               <p>Submit your ſelues vnto the King, as vnto the ſuperiour.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Field</hi> for <hi>Robert Mylbourne.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25909:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25909:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, <hi>TO BIE,</hi> BY THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD, Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Primate of <hi>England, and Metropolitane.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſent vnto your Grace this ſhort Sermon, not for any Synopticall skill to be ſeene in it, (for how ſhould a Minſtrell pipe artificially, wanting his ouerlip?) but onely for the good I am perſwaded may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound by it to the people of this Land, my brethren and kinſmen according to the fleſh. For, whereas they are borne in hand, and ſome, for want of better grace, are made ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleeue, that the Regiment of the Church peculiarly belongeth to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the prerogatiue of his office; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb facs="tcp:25909:3"/>admit no coine for currant money, but that which cometh from his Mint, and hath his Image and ſuperſcription on it: here they may ſee the ground of that leud opinion ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at leaſt, if not razed; and, as it were, a Trophee of the Kings ſupreame power ouer his ſubiects, as well in matters Spirituall as Temporal, by force of Gods word, as by dint of ſword, eſtabliſhed. So as there is likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, that ſuch, who haue any ſparke of the good Spirit, which leadeth into truth, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in them, vpon ſo euident a manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their error, will be won at length to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it, and leaue banding themſelues in the Popes quarrell againſt the Lord and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed: the onely <hi>Helena,</hi> in a manner, that this day troubleth the ſtate of our <hi>Greece.</hi> For (to appeale to all that be acquainted, either with the preſent conſtitution of our bodie politique, or with the true complexion of our Church) what other maligne humour, to ſpeake of, doth attaint the health of the one; or blemiſh, disfigure the beautie of the other? If this cloud were ſcattered, Lord, how bright would our Hemiſphere ſhine? If this mud <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25909:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Sermon, if thou be not too parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, thou ſhalt find, to the comfort and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of all true ſubiects, the Kings title fairely pleaded againſt the Pope; and proued to be agreable to the written word of God, and to the example of the Church, when it was yet in the prime and flower of her age. If our Romiſh Rabbines could ſhew the like evidence for the Popes ſoueraigntie ouer the King, their followers (I muſt confeſſe) were to be borne with in the courſe of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings that way: but it being a thing, which the Scripture doth not onely not warrant, but vtterly diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uow, and which is ſo farre from correſponding to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of the primitiae Church, that it is antipode and quite oppoſite to the ſame, no pretence, though never ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable will abſolue their doing from guilt of notorious diſloyaltie, who contrarie to their allegeance do abandon the King in a right of his inheritance allowed by God; and as if that abuſe were too litle, moſt vnnaturally do abette againſt him an out-landiſh Prelate in a moſt vnlawfull claime, by meare forgerie at firſt vſurped, and euer ſince by force and fraud ſupported and maintained. Were it
<pb facs="tcp:25909:4"/>that the State made for it, and with fire and faggot did ſeeke to eſtabliſh it, as a ſignet meet for Sions right hand, as heretofore it hath done; their fault would appeare the leſſe, and they the more excuſable, by how much death is of that terrible aſpect, and hath ſo grim and ghaſtly a looke with it, that it is enough to quaile the courage of a right ſtout champion, euen in a right good cauſe, as we have experience of the ſame in <hi>Peter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 26.</note> But ſith that by the poſitiue law of the land it is now cleane put downe, and as a baſtard brat of Babylon baniſhed the Countrie, we may iuſtly proclaime them for miniſters of Antichriſt, that in heart vndutifully wiſh, and by wicked practiſes audaciouſly attempt, or vnder hand couertly, but craftily, broake the reſtoring of it among vs againe. Wiſedome would, they did looke about them, and be ſure, before they take ſo maine a leape, leſt lighting againſt the rocke of perdition, they be cruſhed to peeces with the fall. For how light account ſoeuer they make of the matter, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſlightly ſentence it as pettie treſpaſſe, or veniall offence, but cenſureth it deeply, as a damnable ſinne, for ſubiects to ſpurne againſt the ſuperiour powers, as through their ſides thruſting at God himſelfe, whoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance they be, and whoſe roome, next and immediatly vnder him, they do by ſpeciall aſſignement from him occupie. And if ſo grieuous a penaltie as the Apostle threatens be to be inflicted vpon ſuch as reſiſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magiſtrate, abuſing his power to protect idolatry, and to root out the name of Chriſt and his Goſpell, as the Emperours, then being heathen, did; how do not they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the vttermoſt rigor of hell torments, that withſtand their godly and chriſtian King employing the authoritie
<pb facs="tcp:25909:4"/>giuen him of God to Gods glory, and to the benefit of the people committed to his charge? They would thinke much to be conycacht in any worldly buſineſſe they take in hand, though neuer ſo triuiall: How happeneth then, that they let themſelues be thus ſenſibly gulled in a caſe of greateſt moment, importing no leſſe then their bodies and ſoules be worth? They are ſurely bewitched, elſe they wold neuer either by perſwaſion be inueigled, or by allurement entiſed, or by violence enforced to ſuch an impietie, as to leaue their duety to the King, which God by expreſſe charge hath impoſed vpon them, and to cleane vnto the Pope as a ſuperiour commander, whom God hath inſcoffed with no ſuch priuiledge. The Scripture hath foretold of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that he indeed would aſpire vnto ſuch an eſtate, and in proceſſe of time ſhould atchieue it, and for a certaine ſpace hold it, till God put in the heart of Kings, to call for their owne againe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.</note> and with one accord and ioynt conſent to pull the beaſt downe as faſt as euer they ſet him vp; as already in part we ſee come to paſſe. But for any perſon, to whom Kings by Gods appointment ſhould ſubmit their ſwords and ſcepters, and may lawfully neither draw the one nor weild the other but at his becke and liking onely, they may aſſoone find a man in the Moone as ſuch a one aſſigned there. Let them then take heede, I aduiſe them, how to picke a thanke and curry fauour with the Pope, they incurre the diſpleaſure of the King: leſt fearing to be beate with a paper rod, they procure themſelues a whipping with quicke Scorpions; leſt flying a painted ſmoke, they run headlong into a hot burning fire; and ſhunning an imagined <hi>Scylla,</hi> fall ouer helmet and creſt into an eſſentiall <hi>Charybdis.</hi> For aſſuredly as the Popes
<pb facs="tcp:25909:5"/>bleſſing when it is at the beſt, and poured out in his fuliest horn, is ſcarce worth a good ſhoebuckle; ſo his curſe, though with bell booke and candle, is but as a fillip or fleabiting in effect: whereas diſobedience to the King doth bring the offenders to vndoubted ruine, as here for the preſent, ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally in the world to come.<note place="margin">Spem pretio non emam.</note> 
               <hi>Sannio</hi> in <hi>Terence,</hi> as ſimple as he was, yet would not buy a pig in a poke, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the prouerb: for ſo he knew he might haply be chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and disburſe his money to his owne diſaduantage. But theſe be ſo ſottiſh, nay ſtupid, that they ſticke not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to aduenture all their wealth temporall and eternal, in a ſhip that hath a maine breach in the bottome, and ſo is no ſooner lanched out from the ſhore into the deepe, but it ſinkes ſtreight, and is ſure to miſcarie without hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. They might do far better, and ſhew more diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a great deale, to anſwer the Popes ſolliciters in that wicked motion, as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> did the harlot <hi>Lais</hi> in another vnreaſonable demand: <hi>Tanti poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere non emo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> We liſt not buy a rue-bargaine ſo deare. He hath good lucke if he run not into forfeiture, that ſeals an obligation, and neuer takes notice of the condition; he may well come to beſhrew himſelfe and ſit downe with loſſe, that ſtrikes hands before he be throughtly made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the match; he is not like to win the game that playes his cardes at randon as they be dealt, without ſo much as looking whether he followeth ſute or no: And are not they worthy to periſh with Antichriſt, that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his tyrannicall vſurpation as a chiefe article of their Creed, and therefore not onely inwardly to be aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto,<note place="margin">In their Caſes of conſcience, the 55. Article</note> but openly to be profeſſed, though death enſue, before they haue well ſearched whether it be proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:25909:5"/>to the analogy of faith expreſſed in the Scriptures, the onely authentical and ſelf-complete rule of all true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciſme? It will not ſerue their turne before God to ſay, ſuch and ſuch learned men ſo informed vs; no more then it did the Iewes, which gaue their voices to Chriſts crucifying, that the Scribes and Phariſees, and high Prieſt had induced them ſo to do. They would be loth to cut their coate after anothers meaſure, or to beſpeake their ſhooes by anothers last; for ſo they might be made either too ſtraite, and wring them; or ouer wide, and not fit them. What mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell then, if they ſtray from the right faith, who frame their iudgement to the opinion of other, of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge perhaps profound enough, and neuer exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether it be anſwerable to the platforme of ſound doctrine? Truth is not pinned to the ſchoole doores, nor tyed to the girdle of great Clearkes, but is confined onely within the limits of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And as no gold was accounted holy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Temple, ſo there is no doctrine to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned Catholicke, but what hath his warrant and ground there. If all that take vpon them the name of Teachers in the Church, were <hi>ipſo facto</hi> inſpired of God, and Orthodoxall, the danger were not ſo great, nor the caution ſo needfull: but ſince all is not gold that gliſtereth, nor euerie one that pretends well, intends well, but there be ſwarmes of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets abroad in the world, ſuch as can ſay one thing, and thinke another: carrie bread in the one hand, and a ſtone in the other: ſuch as in painted boxes for whoſeſome Triacle ſell ranke poyſon: vnder a
<pb facs="tcp:25909:6"/>pleaſant baite, hide a deadly hooke: and vpon counterfeit mettall, ſet a right ſtampe: Scorpions that haue amiable faces, but ſtinging tailes: Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles, that vnder teares can ſhrowd treaſon: Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian <hi>Sinons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dicebant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſed mente alta praua ſtruebant.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: a metaphor taken from foundations of houſes, which are laid deepe. <hi>Epicharmus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </note> that vnder a ſmooth tale, can bring in a Troian horſe: Homericall hypocrites, that can ſpeake well, but diſſemble deeply: doubtleſſe in matters of Religion, eſpecially in this controuerſed point of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conſequence, they cannot be ouer-cautelous and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect. And truly hence it is, that we daily ſee ſo many ouerſeene and ſeduced, becauſe they practiſe not the precept of the wittie Poet, in being miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; nor follow the counſell of the ſententious Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, in not being ouer-credulous; nor take warning of the Diuine both Euangeliſt and Apoſtle, in not beleeuing euerie ſpirit.<note place="margin">1. Iob. 4.</note> Wherefore I reade them, as they tender their owne welfare and ſoules health, not to ſuffer themſelues longer, like hooded hawkes, to be caried blindfolded they wot not whither, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> foole was led to the ſtockes:<note place="margin">Prouerb. 7.</note> but to trie before they truſt, and not to follow the opinion of any man, how Encyclopaedian ſoeuer,<note place="margin">Nullius addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti iurare in verba magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftri.</note> till they haue throughly ſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and bolted it, and by due proofe and diſquiſition found it to be floure, not bran; good ware, not raffe. In which behalfe, foraſmuch as the ſmall Tract fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing promiſeth to miniſter no ſmall furtherance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, it ſhall not be amiſſe without longer prologue or further prefacing, to referre them vnto it. Onely I requeſt them to peruſe it with indifferencie, all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious affection ſet aſide; and then in Gods name let them iudge, and doe as they ſee cauſe. I can
<pb facs="tcp:25909:6"/>but perſwade: it lieth in them whether they will yeeld or no. In the meane while, good Reader, I bid thee heartily farewell.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Stainton</hi> in the ſtreete, in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Durrham.</hi> Nouemb. <hi>5.</hi> Ann. <hi>1618.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Tho. Ingmethorpe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="tetrastich">
            <pb facs="tcp:25909:7"/>
            <head>The ſumme of this Sermon, for memorie ſake, may be abſtracted into this Tetraſtich.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ACtum eſt de Papa, perijt ſuprema poteſtas,</l>
               <l>Quam ſupra Reges vendicat enſiferos:</l>
               <l>Diuina ſiquidem Scriptura teſte, bicornem</l>
               <l>Conſtituit Mitram poſt Diadema Deus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>In Engliſh.</head>
               <l>ALas for you, Sir Pope,</l>
               <l>Your ſupreme powre proues voide:</l>
               <l>To Kings 'tis due by right,</l>
               <l>Whom long it hath annoide.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25909:7"/>
            <head>A SERMON VPON THE WORDS OF SAINT PAVL:</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Let euerie ſoule be ſubiect vnto the higher powers.  <bibl>Rom. 13.1.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all doctrinall poſitions ſet abroach in the ſchoole of Antichriſt, (men, brethren, and fathers, well beloued in the Lord) there is not a more errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous paradoxe, eſtranged nay abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from all both diuine and humane literature, then that which giues the Biſhop of Rome preheminence ouer Kings and Emperours.<note place="margin">Innocent. <hi>3.</hi> in decretal. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanceth the Pope in ſtate aboue the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour as much as the Sunne in brightneſſe ſurmounts the Moone, and as gold in value exceeds lead. Gelaſ. diſt. <hi>95.</hi>
               </note> Howbeit as among the Philoſophers there was not an opinion ſo abſurd, but there were euer ſome auditors as abſurd, to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it: ſo, as harſh an aſſertion as this is, and vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourie, yet there want not euen amongſt vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who intoxicated with the cup of Babyloniſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment, not onely not diſtaſte the ſame as vnca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, but as truly Orthodoxall, approue of it and embrace it; and that with ſuch reſolution of minde and heate of affection, that many ſtick not in defence thereof to venture goods, lands, liuing, and libertie;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25909:8"/>and ſome more deſperate then the reſt,<note place="margin">Like the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, who for their errors &amp; credits ſake, wilfully made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſclues away: Aug. cpiſt. <hi>50.</hi> ad Bonif.</note> to loſe their liues. For the better informing therefore of mens iudgements and conſciences in that behalfe, I haue thought it opereprecious for the preſent, and worth the while, to trauell ſomewhat in that argument, and to let them ſee, vnleſſe they hoodwink and blindfold themſelues for the nonce, that Kings and Princes by Gods ordinance are conſtituted ſupreme Gouernors of their dominions, without ſubordination or depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to any earthly ſuperiour; and the ſoueraigne power which the biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> claimeth ouer them, to be meerely tranſcendent, Antichriſtian, vniuſt, and vſurped.<note place="margin">A ſtring more then needful to be harped on in theſe Ieſuited cayes: wherein traitors go for martyrs, and rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt Princes, doth maske vnder the vizar, and is enameled with the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name of Catholicke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion.</note> And for this purpoſe, I haue purpoſely ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled out and choſen for my Text, the parcel of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture euen now propoſed, as promiſing much that way. For indeed it containeth an abſolute rule, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetting downe both the ſubiect from whom, and the obiect to whom ſubiection is due. Which two points duly debated and diſcuſſed, it will euidently appeare, among other wholeſome documents, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of right is aboue or vnderling to other, the ciuill Magiſtrate or the Pope; and conſequently who do better, or be more to blame in the title of Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, we, who ſtand for the King againſt the Pope, or our vnnaturall countrymen, who take part with the Pope againſt the King. The King of Kings grant, that in the audience of Chriſtian ſubiects, I may not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruite intreate of ſo important, proſitable, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie a Subiect.</p>
            <p>And firſt, touching the parties liable to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, our Apoſtle declareth who they be, in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25909:8"/>words <hi>(euery ſoule.)</hi> Where by <hi>ſoule</hi> is meant,<note place="margin">According to the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for which <hi>Targhum</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly hath <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Leuit. <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a kind of ſpeech wherein the whole is noted by the part.</note> not the ſpirits of men ſeparated from their bodies, for they be either in heauen if good, or if bad in hell, as Scripture affirmeth and informeth vs, and ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the reach of any earthly Potentate to be able to touch them: but according to the figure ſynecdoche, the ſoule being the nobler part of man, is put for the whole man compoſed of ſoule and body. A figure of ſpeach very familiar in holy Writ, and much fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented. To this is annexed the particle <hi>(euery)</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> euery ſoule, which being a note of vniuerſalitie, and neither here nor elſewhere throughout the whole volume of Gods booke, by any reſtraint of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in this caſe abridged, it cannot but make the propoſition generall and extend vniuerſally &amp; ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to all. For the perſons to whom ſubiection is to be yeelded, the Apoſtle likewiſe expreſſeth them by the name of higher powers: whereby is ſignified the ciuill Magiſtrate in euery commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, of what forme of gouernment ſoeuer it be, as the King,<note place="margin">Tres regimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis formae: Monarchia, Ariſtocratia, Democratia. Plato in polit. &amp; Ariſtot. l. 3. polit. cap. 5. &amp; lib. 6. Ethic. cap. 16.</note> where the ſtate is <hi>Monarchicall;</hi> the <hi>Optimates,</hi> where it is <hi>Ariſtocraticall;</hi> the people, where <hi>Democraticall.</hi> For it is not to be thought, that Chriſt came to abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, to aboliſh or repeale any lawfull ciuill policie formerly eſtabliſhed, but by planting therein his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall kindome, ſtanding eſpecially in the motions of the heart, of the Synagogue of ſathan to make it the Church of God. The outward adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof, may well be fitted, and made agree to any faſhion of politicall regiment, without impeachment or preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the ſame. In ſo much, that where they meete a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25909:9"/>a Chriſtian commonwealth &amp; the Church are no longer to be held for two diſtinct bodies, as iron and clay, which will not ſticke together: but ſo grow into one, like the ſience and the ſtocke wherein it is graffed, that they become in a maner <hi>termini conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibiles,</hi> as Logitians ſpeake, termes <hi>equiualent,</hi> or as Grammarians ſay, <hi>ſynonymaes,</hi> words that import all one matter. And of them may be verified, that which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> two dreames of the Kine and of the eares of corne,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.</note> 
               <hi>They are both one.</hi> By which their combination &amp; mutual dependence, the wel-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of either is not onely no whit empaired, but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bettered and amended. As may be exemplified, not to inſtance forreine countries, in this natiue and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Realme of ours, the Lords name be praiſed for it. And pray we inceſſantly and from the ground of our hearts, that as he vouchſaſed of his goodneſſe to ſtitch them together againe, when by force of Romiſh tyranny they were rent aſunder; ſo now they may be wedded in a perfect and perpetuall mariage, neuer to part nor be diuorced any more. The ſeueral parcels of the account thus caſt, the ſum of the whole in groſſe by iuſt Arithmeticke amounteth to this much: that all men, of what condition or ſtate ſoeuer they be, do ſtand obliged and bound by dutie to ſubiect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in all things to the temporall Magiſtrate, where they inhabite and conuerſe, without reſiſtance. A doctrine of ſingular conſequence, and to many very good vſes ſeruiceable. To giue you a taſte of ſome of the principall and moſt materiall points, for time will not ſuffer me to touch them all in particular.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:25909:9"/>
            <p>Firſt, it ditteth vp the mouthes of Anabaptiſts, who dreaming of an equalitie purchaſed by Chriſt, diſclaime all Magiſtracy,<note place="margin">See the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes between the true Chriſt and the ſalſe, put forth by certaine of that crue in Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiluania, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the ſeuenth</note> as a calling altogether vnlawfull for Chriſtians to exerciſe. As though true Chriſtianity and Magiſtracy were things incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible, and as fire and water did expell one the other. Whereas in very truth there is no more repugnancy between them, then betweene heate &amp; light, which though they be <hi>diſparata</hi> diſtinct things, and in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſeiunct and ſeparate, yet are found to concurre well enough in <hi>eodem tertio,</hi> as in the globe or body of the Sunne. If Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had bene of their minde, he would no doubt, in this his treaty of a Magiſtrate, haue branded it with ſome marke of diſlike or other, and not blaze it with colours of applauſe and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, as he doth. Neither would he ſo vehemently haue called for obedience vnto rulers, but rather haue incenſed and ſet the people at defiance againſt them. To ſay, this of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhewes, that Chriſtians may be ſubiect to an heathen Magiſtrate, but proues not that a Chriſtian may play the Magiſtrate himſelfe, is no ſound collection of a iudicious mind, but a friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſuggeſtion of a light braine: for if Chriſtians with ſafe conſcience may be ſubiect to an heathen Magiſtrate, why not rather (I report me to you) to one that is a Chriſtian, &amp; better qualified? And if it be lawfull for a Chriſtian to be a ſubiect, why not a King, ſince ſubiection ſeemeth more to preiudicate the libertie of the Goſpel, then to reigne &amp; beare rule? Much might be ſaid in conſutation of theſe phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, but becauſe I ſee they rather need to be purged for phrenſie then informed by diuinitie, I leaue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25909:10"/>the caſe longer with them, and at this time onely for their healths ſake put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in mind of <hi>Anticy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naniget An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticyras.</note> where, for ſayling thither, they may be ſure of <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leborus</hi> enough to ſcoure their humorous braines withall. And if they thinke much to be ſeene arriue and land there, let them, by my aduice, hold on their courſe, till they come to <hi>Vtopia,</hi> or ſome ſuch <hi>Vdemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> coaſt. For there, if any where, it is likely they may find entertainment, and obtaine licence to erect their new fangled architecture, the confuſed chaos and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> platforme of their turbulent and tumultuous Anarchy. Sure, ſober and diſcreet Chriſtians, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the light of nature haue the Canon of Gods word to direct them, will none of it.</p>
            <p>Againe, this marres the market of the Romane Clergie, who chalenge an exemption from all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powers, as a legacie bequeathed them of God, by vertue of their ſpirituall function. For whereas Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exacteth obedience of all men, none of any vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation excepted, as by the tenour of his ſpeech is more then euident, it argueth plainly, that by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> which is agreed of all ſides to be canonicall and authentick, Clerks if they be men, do owe ſubiection to the Magiſtrate no leſſe then lay men. The inference is not mine, that ye ſhould ſuſpect it as new fangled and partiall. It is the ancient Fathers owne, of whom I haue borrowed it, and from whom the Church of Rome would ſeeme to ſwarue in none of her Theoremes,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom 23. in epiſt. ad Romanes.</note> and proceedings. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> in his 23. Homily vpon the Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the Romanes, out of the ſame words now in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25909:10"/>hand, maketh the ſame deduction, that by that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall precept of the Apoſtle all are concluded vnder ſubiection to the Magiſtrate, Prieſts (to vſe his owne terms) as wel as ſecular men.<note place="margin">Theophyl. in cap. 13. epiſt. ad Romanos.</note> 
               <hi>Theophylact</hi> as he traceth the footſteps of <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in moſt of his expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo in this he iumpeth iuſt with him and followeth him to a haire. To whom ſubſcribeth <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In cap. 13. ep. ad Rom. In Epiſt. ad Roman. Epiſt. lib. 3. cap. 100.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth <hi>Oecumenius</hi> vary from them. Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt maketh vp a part in the ſame harmony, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the later Popes ſing the cleane contrarie note. But it is no newes to heare Popes contradict one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Muſicke of the Papacie is compact almoſt if not altogether of ſuch diſcords, which make a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody fit for hell and Diuels to daunce by the meaſures thereof. Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> though he ſaw not all things,<note place="margin">Ad Senoneoſ. Arcbiepiſcop. epiſt. 42. <hi>about the yeare</hi> 1140.</note> by reaſon of the blindneſſe of his time wherewith he was ouerwhelmed, as he is taxed in the Prouerb, <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardus non vidit omnia:</hi> yet as thicke as the miſt was, he could deſcry this interpretation for true through it, and not onely condeſcended to it himſelfe, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured by ſtrong perſwaſion to poſſeſſe others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and that <hi>Eugenius</hi> a Biſhop of Rome himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, with apprehenſion of the ſame. And if theſe gray haires, theſe old Fathers had all held their peace, the caſe is ſo clearely reſolued in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by practiſe of the Church ſo abundantly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and confirmed, that none but ſuch as haue loſt their eies, or wilfully cloſe them againſt the light of apparent proofe, can chuſe but ſee it. To beginne with the Prieſts of the old Teſtament, that they were euer ſubiect to the Prince, and vnder his <hi>Coram nobis,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:25909:11"/>it is frankly and freely confeſſed by Doctors of their owne, that I ſhall not need to ſpend any time, nor to beſtow any paines about the further prouing of that point. And for the Goſpell, that by it the ſtate of Princes was neither abated nor altered, but remained ſtill the ſame it was before, and ſo the Princes hand no more reſtrained from his Clergy then from his other ſubiects, it may alſo by many manifeſt teſtimonies of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnauoidably be euinced. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant, how that Chriſt charged the Scribes and high Prieſts as well as others, will all duty to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the right and intereſt of God, which in all things, and at all times, and of all perſons ought to be forepriſed and kept inuiolate, ſafe reſerued. And for his owne part, when he was conuented, arraigned and condemned by the Romane Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.</note> though but a deputie: he was ſo farre off from excepting againſt him, as one that tranſgreſſed the bounds &amp; went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the limits of his authority in medling with him both a Prieſt and a Prophet, that he dutifully ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe vnto his will, &amp; ingenuouſly agnized his power ouer him to be from heauen, notwithſtanding his iudgement againſt him was moſt iniurious and wrongfull. And if Chriſt had freed his Apoſtles from the iuriſdiction of the Magiſtrate, would Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> think you, wittingly haue forfeited and betraied his right,<note place="margin">Act. 25.</note> when of his owne accord he appealed to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and made his perſonall appearance and apologie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his tribunall ſeate, vnrequired? No, no; it is well knowne Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was of that puiſſant ſpirit and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danted courage, that rather then he would haue ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25909:11"/>done, he would haue incurred &amp; vndergone any euen the ſharpeſt penaltie, yea though he had bene there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by authoritie vrged and prouoked. And whom, I pray, doth Saint <hi>Peter</hi> warne,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> to ſubmit themſelues vnto the King, as vnto the ſupereminent, were they not his fellow Elders as well as the reſt of the faithful, whom a little after he importuneth to feed the flocke of God?<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> As for the title of kingly Prieſthood attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to the Church of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> it maketh nothing againſt this, if it be conſtrued aright. For it muſt not be vnderſtood of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdoms of this world, as though the Apoſtles meaning had bin that Prieſts, which in former times were ſubiect to the King, were now by meanes of the Goſpell, become kings within themſelues, and may do as they liſt, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulment and feare of law,<note place="margin">Dorm. fol. 40.</note> as <hi>Dorman</hi> that drowſie <hi>Endymion</hi> and his <hi>Louanian</hi> conſort dreame in their ſleep: but the Church was ſtyled with that appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion onely in regard of the kingdome of heauen, as <hi>Iohannes de Pariſiis</hi> a bird of their own feather,<note place="margin">Ioh. de Pariſ. cap. 18.</note> wel no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, &amp; all the ancient Fathers, <hi>vno ore,</hi> with one voice ſo expound the place. With Scripture doth accord the vſe of the Church for many ages ſucceeding. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the Eccleſiaſticall ſtories from top to toe, or if your leaſure or skill will not ſerue you, conſult the beſt learned Diuine amongſt our aduerſaries you can come by; and if he can produce vnto you one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counterfeit preſident to the contrary, but that the Prieſt, for the ſpace of a thouſand yeares after Chriſt, was ſtill vnder the checke and correction of the Prince, then let me beare the blame and ſhame of a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25909:12"/>falſe teacher. Truth it is, religious Princes haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Clergimen extraordinary fauour in their Courts, both for their Maiſters and for their meſſage ſake; but neuer Prince, look who enlarged their liberties moſt, did ſo abſolutely releaſe them from the bond of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, but that himſelfe might at his pleaſure call them to a reckoning of their doings, and proceed to puniſhment againſt them, if the caſe ſo required: vntill ſuch time as the Antichriſt of Rome, as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſticated of him long before vnder the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whore of Babylon,<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.</note> got the maſtery of the Kings of the earth, and bound them in ſuch awe, that they durſt not ſo much as queſtion; much leſſe croſſe any of his deſires or deſignes, though neuer ſo leud, neuer ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trauagant. As a glozer of their owne vpon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals not obſcurely inſinuateth; his words be theſe: <hi>Quaeritur quis exemit Clericum de iuriſdictione Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris, &amp;c.</hi> Queſtion is moued, who exempted the Prieſt from the iuriſdiction of the Emperour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before he was his ſubiect:<note place="margin">Extra. de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorit. &amp; obed cap. 2. in marg</note> 
               <hi>Laurentius</hi> ſaith, the Pope exempted him by conſent of the Emperour. But what though the Emperour at the Popes moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had endowed them with an immunitie and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitie full out as large as is pretended? You muſt know, it is one thing to pleade a priuiledge by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graunt from the King, and another, to intitle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto it in the right of Gods word, &amp; to claime it as their owne heritage properly belonging and inſeparably vnited to their ſacred function. So that ye ſee, howſoeuer it be diſguiſed vnder the maske &amp; vizar of Religion, it goeth cleane againſt the ſtreame
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25909:12"/>of Gods word, and is in truth no better then flat rebellion againſt his Vicegerents and Lieutenants here on earth, for Prieſts, vnder the colour and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of Gods law, to ſequeſter themſelues from the gouernance and chaſtiſement of the Prince. And this concluſion ſhall vndoubtedly go for currant, and ſtand for Catholicke, though all the kennell of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, Seminarians, and other Antichriſtian hounds do barke and baule neuer ſo with open mouth againſt it as hereticall.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, Princes may hence take a ſcantling, how farre their authoritie and charge ſtretcheth, as well in reſpect of the perſons ouer whom, as of the cauſes wherein they haue to gouerne and beare the ſword. For ſith the holy Ghoſt requireth ſubiection of all in generall, and that ſimply without limitation of any kind of matter, it is a ſequele paſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felling of both Seminaries,<note place="margin">A Gordiꝰ knot paſt looſing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Pope, like Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, come with his ſword &amp; chop it all to peeces.</note> and lay all their heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that Princes within their owne Realmes and territories are ſupreme gouernours, as of all perſons, be they Prieſts, Prelates, Popes, or whatſoeuer, ſo likewiſe in all things, whether they concerne the firſt or ſecond table of the Law of God. For where the Spirit of God compriſeth all, they do but delude themſelues, who vpon any pretence exclude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And where the Spirit of God ſpeaketh indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely and at large, not diſtinguiſhing of the things wherein ſubiects are, or are not to obey; it is vaine for ſubiects of any ſort, to capitulate and indent with their Prince, in what caſes forſooth they will be at command, and in what they will not. Whereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25909:13"/>that popiſh Princes who ſuffer themſelues to be perſwaded, that all Eccleſiaſticall both perſons and matters are cleane without the compaſſe of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, and pertaine not to their princely charge, and thereupon refuſe to haue to do with Prieſts their doctrine and doing, or to deale in any other occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of ſpirituall nature, leauing them to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire conduct of Churchmen, &amp; neuer regarding whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be managed aright or no, are deeply guilty before almightie God, and haue much to anſwer for breach of dutie in the execution of their office. As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thoſe reformed Princes, who hauing the word of God for their warrant, and the examples of the godly Kings of Iſrael and the religious Emperours of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome for their preſident, do by due courſe of law prouide that all men do their dutie, Prieſts as well as other; and that Gods true Religion be maintained within their dominions, as well as ciuill iuſtice mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, do no more then what of right they may do, and of bounden dutie ſhould do. And therefore it was an egregious, ſawcie, diſloyall and irreligious part of <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> Archbiſhop of Canterbury,<note place="margin">Math. Pariſ. in Henrico 2. anno 1164. Guil Newbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>retu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ang lib. 2. cap. 16.</note> when the King then regnant, inflamed with deſire of iuſtice, ſought to puniſh certaine Clergie men for diuers robberies and murthers committed, whereof they ſtood detected and conuicted before the Iudges in their circuits; openly to reſiſt and oppoſe himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as he did. And truly the Biſhop of Rome had done far better for the credit and reputation of his Church, if, when he canonized him for a Saint, he had condemned him for a traitor. For who, not alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25909:13"/>addicted to the Romane ſuperſtition, will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to thinke wel of that religion which obtrudeth vpon the people to be worſhipped a rebell and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor againſt his Prince? of whom the maiſters of Paris made it a diſputable point, whether he were ſaued or damned. And one in fauour of the Church of Rome extolling him to the clouds for a Martyr;<note place="margin">Rogerus Normannus.</note> another an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, he was worthy to die as a malefactor, for that he durſt preſume to thwart &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>termand the pere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory command of his Prince, whom God would haue in all things with all reuerence &amp; ſubmiſſion obeyed, his owne diuine dominion and due no way violated. And in caſe the Kings pleaſure be repugnant to the will of God, though the rule be generall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act. 5.</hi> The King as mount Sinai may not be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched without mortal offence, much leſſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently aſſaulted The true pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall import of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the very abſtract quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of a ſubiects dutie. The ſuperiority which the Pope vſurpeth ouer Princes, is here ſtript &amp; whipt, being the moſt venimous Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>katrice that euer poiſoned the Church of Chriſt.</note> that <hi>God is rather to be obeyed then man;</hi> yet the law of God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth no man by oppoſition to rebecke him, but abſolutely bindeth all men with patience to ſubmit themſelues vnto his ſword, and to endure the penalty which he ſhall inflict vpon them for refuſing to do as he commandeth. The one way leadeth to rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the innate fruite of Romiſh Catholiciſme, abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God and good men; the other to perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake, the badge of true Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whereby man is tried, &amp; by his trial God glorified.</p>
            <p>Further yet, the vlcerate Apoſteme of the Popes vſurpation, in taking vpon him to depoſe Princes, and diſpoſe their kingdoms at his pleaſure, if they chance to ſtand in his light, or any way to eclipſe the bright beames of his vnlimited Maieſtie, by the interpoſition of their earthly domination, is here cruſhed and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the quicke. If his Holineſſe had any ſuch coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25909:14"/>power ouer Princes allotted him by God, as he challengeth, and his flattering paraſites ſoothe him vp in, doubtleſſe S. <hi>Paul,</hi> hauing ſo fit an opportunitie as here is offered him, would haue giuen the faithfull ſome inkling of it. But in that he deuideth the Church into two parts onely, ſubjects and higher powers, not mentioning any third ſtate ſuperiour to Princes; he giueth that Papall fancie ſo deadly a ſtripe, as all the balme in Gilead will not ſerue to heale the wound. For except we ſhall traduce the Apoſtles diuiſion as defectiue and inſufficient, it muſt needs be granted,<note place="margin">A plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration to the eye where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the mount of the Romiſh ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted.</note> that the Biſhop of Rome is included in one of the two ſorts; either he muſt go in the tale of ſubiects, or be ranked with the higher powers. But among the higher powers he can haue no place, as by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text is plaine, they being there decyphered to be ſuch as beare the ſword, and to whom tribute is payable, the ſpecificall and, as I may ſay, characteriſticall notes of the ſecular Magiſtrate, and ſo not originally inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and incorporate in the office of a Biſhop, as the Pope is, whom Chriſt by ſpeciall prohibition hath interdicted all ciuill dominion, whereof the ſword is the enſigne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math. 20. Mark. 10.</hi> This letteth not but Biſhops may lawfully deale in ciuill cauſes, being thereunto cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed by the higher powers.</note> and tribute the earneſt. Wherfore ſeeing that the Biſhop of Rome cannot be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the higher powers, it followeth, not as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary or coniecturall ſuppoſition, but as a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry concomitant, and certainty more then geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, that he is to be accounted but in the number of ſubiects. And they by Gods owne inſtitution and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance are bound to obey, not licenſed to domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neere and tyrannize ouer Princes, as the Biſhop of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25909:14"/>Rome in the pride of his heart arrogantly preſumeth to do.<note place="margin">An vlcer that cannot be pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with too ſharp a naile.</note> This Analyſis of the place, howſoeuer the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected cannot well brooke nor digeſt with patience, as derogatory to the prerogatiue of the Pope, whom they take to be their <hi>ſummum bonam;</hi> yet is it agreeable to the vniforme confeſſion of the Primitiue Church, which euermore acknowledged Princes to be ſuperiour to all, and ſubject to none but God; as by the verdict of <hi>Tertullian, Optatus, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> and other of the ancient Fathers, if need were, and time and place would permit, might more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly and at large be made good. Ridiculous it is, and worthy the ſmeare of a black coale, which the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, to bleare the eyes of his ſilly profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes withall,<note place="margin">Extra. de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorit. &amp; obed. c. Solitae. 1. Pet. 2. <hi>The Popes Gloſſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the text.</hi>
               </note> doth comment vpon thoſe words of Saint <hi>Peter, Submit your ſelues vnto the King,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>as vnto the moſt excellent.</hi> For by <hi>(as vnto the moſt excellent)</hi> he would beare them in hand, that the Apoſtle intended a reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blance only, not that the King was very ſo indeed: whereas the particle <hi>(as)</hi> doth there betoken the realty and truth of the matter, like as in that of <hi>Iohn, We ſaw the glorie thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>as the glorie of the onely begotten Sonne.</hi> And yet is this no point ſo inſulſly paraphraſed by reaſon of the terme of doubting (perhaps) wherewith he quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth his ſpeech; as where he a dioyneth without any maner of ſcruple or ſtaggering at all, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid not ſimply, <hi>Submit your ſelues,</hi> but with this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>for Gods ſake;</hi> following therein the tracke of the vulgar verſion, or rather as other reade more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to the Greeke originall, <hi>for the Lords ſake,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25909:15"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as if by thoſe words (as they euer haue had a ſingular grace and dexteritie in tranſſubſtantiating by words) the precept were transformed into a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell:<note place="margin">See the Gloſſe vpon the Chapter.</note> whereas taken in their right ſence, they ſerue ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to giue a ſharper edge vnto it, and to make it more emphaticall. As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> when he had giuen out of the magiſtrate, <hi>He is the miniſter of God,</hi> inferres thereupon,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore ye muſt be ſubject, not becauſe of wrath onely, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prieſt indeed, as cannot be denied, hath a kind of regiment, as wel ouer Princes as priuate men, annexed to his office. In conſideration whereof, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Obey your Ouerſeers.</hi> But this is internall, not externall; perſwaſiue, not compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue; ſpirituall, not temporall; ouer their ſoules, not ouer their bodies, goods and inheritances: and ſo neither hinders the ſubiection of the one, nor is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to the principalitie of the other. For as the King in ſickneſſe may be ruled by Phyſitions, in building by Maſons and Carpenters, in trauelling by guides, in warres by ſouldiers, and by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in affaires of State; yet this diminiſheth nothing of the ſupremacy he hath ouer them: but if theſe or any of them make default againſt any of his lawes, the King for all that by his princely power may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them accordingly: ſo the King may be ruled by his Clergie in matters of doctrine and diſcipline, ſo far forth as they perſwade no other then what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Propheticall and Apoſtolicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But if once they exorbitate from that rule, and become either negligent in their office, or falſe in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25909:15"/>their teaching, or vicious in their liuing, or in plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and practiſing treacherous and perfidious; the King may notwithſtanding by his royall authority, according to the quantity and quality of the offence, lawfully correct them, whether it be by a pecuniary mulct, or by reſtraint of liberty, or by confiſcation of goods, or by the loſſe of life, or otherwiſe, as he ſhall ſee good. But if the King on the other ſide an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer not his duty to God in euery point, the Prieſt muſt not now do the like by him, foraſmuch as God hath not thereunto authorized him.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts office is confined to the word and Sacraments, it extendeth not to the ſword. So that the Prieſt may teach and reproue euen Princes, as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> did <hi>Achab, Nathan Dauid, Iohn Baptiſt Herod:</hi> but by any corporall chaſtiſement to diſcipline the meaneſt ſubiect, much leſſe by ſtrong hand and force of armes to reclaime Princes, and will they nill they, to reduce them to order if they go aſtray, whom God hath reſerued to his owne iudgement, a puniſhment no doubt ſeuere enough; the Prieſt by the reſolution of Gods word, is not onely not permitted, but flatly inhibited ſo to do.</p>
            <p>What words then can ſerue to vtter the huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the length, breadth, depth and thickneſſe of the indignity and wrong which the Biſhop of Rome, of long time hath, and ſtill doth offer vnto Chriſtian Princes? who if they humour him not in euery thing he would haue, tend it neuer ſo directly to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, the deſtruction of the Chriſtian faith, the annoying of their State and peoples, ouer whom
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25909:16"/>God hath ſet them, makes no more ado but depriues them ſtreight of their regal dignity, aſſoiles their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their allegiance; and if they be not ſtrong enough to make their party good and effectuate his proiects,<note place="margin">The Pope can fiſh beſt in troubled water</note> irritates forreine Princes to inuade their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, vpon compact to weare them if they can win them: knowing like a crafty foxe, that ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Princes, as fiſh with baite, are eaſie to be caught by ſuch compoſitions. Certainly if <hi>Tully</hi> himſelfe were now liuing, who for eloquence bare the bel in all the world, he could not with al his Rhetorical colours paint it out ſufficiently, nor with figures of paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignely vociferate, exclaime and inueigh againſt it.</p>
            <p>Were there not of the Kings of Iſrael and Iuda, as the Spirit of God vpbraideth diuers of them, that were ſold vnto wickedneſſe and deuoted to idolatry? yet in the bookes of Kings and Chronicles, you ſhall not find one Prieſt recorded that euer attempted the like againſt any one of them ſo long as that kind of gouernment was afoote. After the coming of Chriſt and irradiation of the Goſpell; of the Emperours that reigned, ſome were infidels, ſome tyrants, ſome here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, ſome apoſtataes; and yet neither the Apoſtles for their time, nor their ſucceſſors for many ages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, did either offer to rebell themſelues, or incited o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to take armes againſt them. If they will not truſt me ſo far, yet I dare ſay they will giue credit to <hi>Othe Friſingenſis,</hi> who was neither Lutheran nor Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, but Hiſtorian of their owne. Thus he writeth: <hi>I haue read ouer and ouer the geſts of the Romane Kings and Emperours, and I find none of them before Henrie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25909:16"/>the fourth, Emperour, excommunicated by the Biſhop of Rome, or depriued of his kingdome.</hi> This deed was done by <hi>Hildebrand, aliàs Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth, a thouſand yeares good after Chriſt. And was there none of all his predeceſſors, thinke you, no not one all that while, that either knew his duty, or would performe it, ſauing <hi>Hildebrand</hi> onely, that furious and ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious monſter? But in him and this exploit of his, if all be true which men of his owne time and religion hiſtorifie of him, is verified the old prouerb,<note place="margin">Similes labris lactucae, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, dignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patella operculum.</note> Like lips like lettuce, ſory crow ſory egge, ſuch a couer ſuch a cup: I meane, like act like author, ſuch a ſtratageme ſuch a contriuer; the one wicked, the other impious; the one ſathanicall, the other diabolicall.</p>
            <p>Fie of that Papall and more then Phariſaicall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that of a Biſhop vnder a Prince, ſhould not onely aſpire and take vpon him to be a Prince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Princes, but counts himſelfe diſparaged and iniuried, if he be not ſuffered to rule the roaſt by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone, as Lord paramount ouer all Princes. He boaſteth himſelfe for Chriſts Vicar and <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor: but this beaſtly and <hi>Lucifer</hi>-like pride miniſters ſtrong ſuſpition, if not aſſurance, that he is neither, but rather that <hi>man of ſinne</hi> and <hi>ſonne of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> foreſpoken of by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that ſhould exalt himſelfe aboue all that is called God; for ſo are Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>I ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> 
               <hi>ye are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that it would pleaſe God at length to illuminate the eyes of our moderne Princes, that they may ſee their owne right, and giue them courage, that they be no longer afraid of that Romane chough, to take
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25909:17"/>from him theſe feathers of theirs, which he guilefully but wrongfully hath embezeled and purloyned away from them,<note place="margin">The power which the Kings of the earth giue to Antichriſt ſhall at length recuile againe to the right owners, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> &amp; implumed himſelfe withall! Wel, ſome ſuch thing there is intimated in the Apocalyps, which thogh it hath not ſo ſpeedy an accompliſhment as we could wiſh, yet we may aſcertain our ſelues that in due time as God in his infallible couſaile hath determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it ſhall come to paſſe. And as <hi>Dalila</hi> ſerued <hi>Sampſon,</hi> ſo ſhall they ſhaue off his furtiue lockes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue him of his triple Crowne, ſtrip him out of his imperiall prerogatiues, reuenues and eſchetes, and make like another Biſhop. Heauen and earth ſhall paſſe, but no title, no iota of Gods word ſhall by any engines neuer ſo politicke, neuer ſo potent, be fruſtrated or defeated. Which being ſo, as ye ſee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gaineſaid,<note place="margin">The diuell and his ſpirit of rebellion do poſſeſſe the hearts of theſe men, and itch to come into their fingers and will not leaue them I thinke, till by ſome diſciplinary exorciſme more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie they be coniured out.</note> O Lord, how feareful is the caſe of thoſe countrimen of ours, who vpon the Popes war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, a ſtrange proud Italian Prieſt, make no bones nor conſcince not onely to diſobey their gracious and liege Soueraigne, but by plots and practiſes to take away his life, and to diſinherite him of that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the earth which God hath entailed to him and his for euer, for the preſeruation of his Church and continuation of his Goſpell amongſt vs: as for his owne part, both by ſword and pen he hath hitherto done, to the admiration of all Chriſtendome; and we do verily truſt in God, wil perſeuere in that reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he and his hopefull progeny after him to the worlds end.</p>
            <p>What? do they thinke the Popes diſpenſation will excuſe their doing from vndutifulneſſe? Alas, Alas;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25909:17"/>that is no armour of proofe: but being made of no better ſtuffe then thin browne paper, is not able to beare out the laſt ſhot that Gods word doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge againſt ſo groſſe and heathenilſh an impietie. But at this time,<note place="margin">Lord that men not baniſhed from their wits ſhould ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully build the bulwarke of conſcience vpon ſo fickle a ground and ſandy a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and hang the ſtate of their ſoules vpon ſo rotten a pin.</note> onely to kill them with their owne weapon, their owne ſword: they crake much of their <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> the very <hi>Atlas</hi> indeed that beares on his ſhoulders the heauen or hell rather of their Schoole-diuinitie; but as ſeemeth, they ſtudy him but lightly and to halfes: elſe they would neuer ſo confidently affie and repoſe themſelues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Popes diſpenſation in that caſe. For he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auoucheth one where, of the law of nature, that it is vnchangeable; and in another place, of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the morall law of God, that they are indiſpenſable. Now who knowes not, that the dutie of a ſubiect towards his Prince, is both deriued from the law of nature, and alſo preſcribed by the fift pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Decalogue? So that by their owne Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Doctors iudgment, which I am ſure they wil not for any good go about to impeach, the ſubiects du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie toward his Prince is inuiolate and paſt diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
            <p>Do they beare themſelues vpon the Popes excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of the King? That plaiſter is too narrow for the ſore too. For by that Eccleſiaſticall cenſure a man is made but as an heathen, <hi>Sicut Ethnicus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> not worſe then an heathen. Now it is manifeſt, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Princes ought to haue obedience exhibited vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> do preciſely enioyne: therefore ſuch as be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated ought
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25909:18"/>not to be debarred of the ſame neither. Beſides, it is a caſe ouerruled by the ioynt conſent of their owne Doctors for the moſt part,<note place="margin">Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable to vnlooſe the naturall bond of duty which ſeruants, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren &amp; wiues do owe vnto their maiſters, fathers, and husbands: much leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to breake that great knot, and as it were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damantine chaine, wherin ſubjects as the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the great family which we call the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, are linked indiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubly to their great father.</note> that by excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither the ſeruant, nor the ſonne, nor the wife be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from the bond of dutie, wherein they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally tyed to their maiſter, father and husband; but the ſubiect doth owe the ſame if not more dutie to his Prince, as who hath his life in his hands; which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the maiſter hath ouer his ſeruant, nor father ouer his ſonne, nor the husband ouer his wife: therfore the Popes exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication of the King, were it currant, as it is counterfeit, blanke, &amp; annulleſt, is no ſufficient diſcharge to acquite his ſubiects from their homage &amp; fealty towards him. O that my voice were as loud &amp; ſhrill as a bell, that I might righ theſe things in the deafe eares of that Adders brood, that viperous gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, our refractarie Papiſts, who to reſtore the worthily ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndoned vſurpation of the Biſhop of Rome, care not how they vilifie the Maieſtie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the authoritie of their ſoueraigne Lord the King: counting it no breach of loyaltie, but a moſt iuſt and honorable exploit, nay a meritorious act before God, for any brother of their confraternity, by any meanes of open aſſault or priuie conſpiracy, to ruine him and his Eſtate: whereas if euery haire of their head were a life, they ought of right to affoord them at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and in his defence. In this diuelliſh and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reſolution, equalling if not ſurpaſſing, the very heathen which knew not God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Concluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this notwithſtanding, if there be any here ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25909:18"/>bankrupt of grace, ſo deſtitute of the Spirit of God, ſo bereft of reaſon and ſenſe,<note place="margin">The vlcer of Babylon is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable.</note> as to dwell ſtill in the contrary opinion, and perſiſt to be the Popes deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vaſſals, factious complices, and traiterous here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques: I call heauen &amp; earth to record this day, that I haue blowne the trumpet and giuen them faire war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: I haue done what lieth in me to retire them from their wicked courſe; their bloud be vpon their owne heads.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The authority wherwith God hath inueſted Princes, and the Popes vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped power can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but as in a counter bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance the one ſcale mounting vp, the other falleth downe: ſo the more ſuppliant men are to the Pope, the more inobedient they grow to their Prince.</note>For our ſelues, my brethren, that already haue ſhaken off the yoke of Popiſh ſeruitude, let vs not, like thoſe Ifraelites, who being in the way towards Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan longed to be in Egypt againe, make our ſelues thrall any more; but let vs hold out without wauering, and conſtantly proclaime all hatefulneſſe and hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt that Romane <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whoſe gouernment (as our fathers to their coſt and ſmart experimented) is but tyranny, his doctrine Antichriſtianitie, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion ſuperſtition, his religion the ſeede of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his diſcipline diſorder and enormitie, and his life iniquity. Let vs, I ſay, abomine and abandon him as the ſworne enemy of our State. And let vs liue in all true ſubiection and Chriſtian obſequiouſneſſe to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, the Lords in dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Annointed ouer vs. He, he is the father of our Country, we the children; let vs honor and obey him: he the Lord, we the ſeruants; let vs feare &amp; reuerence him: he the ſhepheard, we the flocke; let vs be guided by him: he the foundation, we the building; let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye &amp; depend on him: he the roote, we the branches; let vs maintaine him: he the head, we the members;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25909:19"/>let vs defend him. Let vs ſerue him in peace, let vs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond him in warre; let vs with vniformitie of heart &amp; tongue pray for him in both, that God would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him from the hands of all his enemies, bodily and ghoſtly, ſecret and open, forreine and domeſtical, as frequently and in miraculous manner he preſerued our late Soueraigne his moſt gracious handmaiden, queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memorie; that he may long reigne a happy, a godly and an ancient Father in Iſrael. Let vs giue moſt humble and moſt heartie thanks vnto God for him, by whoſe meanes we enioy ſo many, ſo great &amp; ſo ineſtimable benefites, that the Countries round about vs haue cauſe to repine at vs, and to waxe pale for enuie: and for felicitie and all humane happineſſe, this Iland of ours may worthily be reputed to be the peerleſſe parago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole world. Finally continue good Lord, continue the light of thy fatherly countenance toward him for euer, and toward vs his ſubiects the children of thy couenant, that we both here &amp; in the world to come, may magnifie thy goodneſſe, and ſing vnto thy Name with thy bleſſed ſeruants and elect Angels, that melodious hymne and euchariſticall encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticke muſicke, <hi>Praiſe and glorie, and wiſedome and thanks, and honour, and power and might be vnto our God for euermore. Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>To end as I began:</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Let euery ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:25909:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
